# IRVING GÓMEZ MÉNDEZ





## Summary

I am a data scientist that merges the experience in applied statistics with a solid theoretical background in machine learning (random forests, neural networks, support vector machines, recommender systems, etc.) and statistics (inference, regression, Bayesian statistics, multivariate analysis, etc.), who enjoys passing from theory to development of meaningful tech products.

### Portfolio

Bayesian statistics

- Notes: https://irvinggomez.github.io/BayesianStatisticsNotes/intro.html
- Codes: https://github.com/IrvingGomez/BayesianStatistics
- Hierarchical models: https://github.com/IrvingGomez/BayesianHierarchicalIncome

Machine learning

- Notes: https://irvinggomez.com/courses/machinelearning/
- Codes: https://github.com/IrvingGomez/MachineLearning

Probability

• Notes: https://https://irvinggomez.com/courses/probactuarial/

## Computing Skills

Programming Languages: Python, Julia, R Data Visualization: Plotly, Tableau, Shiny

Deep Learning: TensorFlow Big Data: PySpark Bayesian Analysis: PyMC

Other Data Analysis: SPSS, Google Analytics Other Languages: SQL, HTML, CSS, LATEX

# Professional Experience

#### CMKL University, Thailand

#### Assistant Professor

March 2024 - To date

- Development of competencies' syllabus for the B.Eng. in artificial intelligence and computer engineering.
- Teaching undergraduate competencies
  - Statistics: Descriptive statistics, producing data, probability distribution, inference statistics.
  - Artificial intelligence: Reinforcement learning.
  - Mathematics: Vector calculus.

# Universidad Iberoamericana (Ibero-American University), Mexico Lecturer

August 2021 - To date

- Development and improvement of actuarial subjects' syllabus.
- Teaching undergraduate subjects: Bayesian statistics, machine learning, actuarial probability.

# National Electronics and Computer Technology Center (NECTEC), Thailand Postdoctoral Researcher

March 2023 - February 2024

- Geo-statistical analysis for multivariate analysis.
- Spatial statistical inference for identification of regional clusters, and social inequality.
- Bayesian data analysis to assist policy makers.
- Data wrangling of large data sets for its further statistical analysis.

#### Banco del Bajío (Bajio Bank), Mexico

#### **Data Scientist**

July 2021 - February 2023

- Implementation of models in an AutoML framework.
- Improvement of statistical tools for internal fraud detection.
- Translate business and customer needs to technical language to determine the best model and solution.
- Present results and projects' progress on an executive level.
- Development of end-to-end projects to evaluate prospects' credit risk.
- Data wrangling and feature engineering from large databases, merging public and private information sources of heterogeneous data.
- Implementation and evaluation of algorithms to estimate the stability of economic sectors.
- Robust statistical inference to improve prospects' estimations.
- Geo-statistical analysis to assist decision making.

## Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas (Center for Research in Mathematics, CIMAT), Mexico Postgraduate Student in Probability and Statistics

August 2014 - June 2021

- Development and implementation of state-of-the-art random forests algorithms to handle data with missing values.
- Implementation of neural networks for recommender systems with partial information.
- Development of methodologies for detection of illegal traffic of species in America.
- Implementation of methodologies for control quality with heavily censored data.
- Statistical consulting for the automotive industry, improving its warranty management.
- Reliability analysis for the food industry, increasing preference of consumers.
- Teaching assistant in undergraduate and graduate subjects: Statistical inference, statistical models.

# **Academic Qualifications**

Ph.D. in Probability and Statistics
Research Stay
Science and Technology, Inria), Lille, France
M.Sc. in Probability and Statistics  Control de Investigación en Metaméticas (CIMAT) Cuenciusta Marias
Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas (CIMAT), Guanajuato, Mexico
B.Eng. in Mathematics
Exchange Student

# David Sprott Award, 2015

Annual prize granted by the Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas (CIMAT) to the best master's exam in the area of statistics.

### **Publications**

- Gómez-Méndez, Irving and Chainarong Amornbunchornvej (2024). "Income, education, and other poverty-related variables: A journey through Bayesian hierarchical models". In: *Heliyon* 10.6.
- Gómez-Méndez, Irving and Emilien Joly (2023a). "On the consistency of a random forest algorithm in the presence of missing entries". In: *Journal of Nonparametric Statistics*. DOI: 10.1080/10485252.2023.2219783.
- Gómez-Méndez, Irving and Emilien Joly (2023b). "Regression with missing data, a comparison study of techniques based on random forests". In: *Journal of Statistical Computation and Simulation*. DOI: 10.1080/00949655.2022. 2163646.

### Selected Talks

Introduction to probabilistic graphical models and causal reasoning	24
An introduction to causality	22
Consistency of a random forest algorithm with missing entries	20
Some ideas for random forests with missing values	20
Some ideas for random forests with missing values	20

## Certifications

# Languages

$Google\ Analytics$
Data Sets with SQL
SQL for Data Science
$Statistical\ Analysis\ with\ SPSS$

SpanishNativeEnglishFluentPortugueseFluentFrenchBasic

Thai Elemental (learning)